Guide to the Thomas Leiper Kane Papers, 1846-1883
Department of Special Collections
Thomas Leiper Kane Papers,
1846-1883
Special Collections M058
Kane, Thomas Leiper
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchased, 1934.
BIOGRAPHY
Thomas Leiper Kane was a law clerk and Army officer.
Note: for a biographical sketch, see the first folder in the collection.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Thomas L. Kane papers primarily cover his two trips West in 1846-1847, and again, in 1858. There is some material covering the period between these trips and some after 1858. The collection contains letters, diaries, agreements, clippings, notes for articles and lectures, drafts, sketches and some diagrams.
Most of the subject matter relates to the Mormons, their history, migrations, persecutions, and characteristics. Kane also describes in detail the country through which he passed along the Missouri River, across the Isthmus of Panama, and between San Bernardino, Calif., and Salt Lake City, Utah. He also describes the difficulties of a long sea voyage.
A small amount of material relates to the Free Soil question, democracy, and state sovereignty. There is also an account of an Indian massacre, a quasi-biblical history, a "Plea of a condemned man," and a geneology of a branch of Kane's wife's family.
NOTE: Much of this material is in the form of loose notes and drafts and some of it is not in KaneÕs hand.
CONTAINER LIST
- Thomas Leiper Kane - biographical sketch by Mary Schofield, n. d., 7 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Kane letter or journal. Jun. and Jul. 1846.earliest date: Jun. 23. Description of trip up Missouri R. - St. Louis, For [Leavenworth], St. Joseph, Mo. 28 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Kane journal. Jul. 5-7, 1846.St. Joseph, Mo. and up river, description. 8 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Kane notes on trip West [1846]; written several years later, date undetermined. Description of Keokuk, Iowa. 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Kane to his sister. n.d., 6 pp. Describes trip up Missouri R. toward Council Bluffs [1846]. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Kane - Description of Mormon History and Persecution. (Probably notes for book or lecture. History beginning 1830-31). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - a. 17 pp. draft
  - b. 4 pp. draft (similar to above)
  - c. 1 p. notes
  - d. 4 pp. draft
  - e. 2 pp. notes
- Kane - Description of Mormons and their migrations. n.d., notes for book or lecture. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - a. children, 5 pp.
  - b. visions, 4 pp
  - c. characteristics and ideology, 14 pp.
- Notes on Mormon History and Persecution in Missouri and Illinois. 19 pp., general notes. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Summary of history, chiefly 1844 to 1847. includes parts of draft of long letter re. wintering place for Mormons. 19 pp. of which 17 pp. is the letter. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Descriptions of attack on Mormons at [Nauvoo, Ill.] n.d., 2 pp. (Probably 1845 or 46). (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Mormon settlement at Nauvoo. Memo, 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- KaneÕs description of Nauvoo after departure of Mormons [1846]. Probably written in 1847 or later, part not by Kane. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - a. 4 pp. draft
  - b. 12 pp. drafts and notes
- Description of departure of Mormons and season of year [1846] - 1 p. flowery or poetic. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Resolutions at a meeting (presumably in Illinois after expulsion of Mormons) [1846]. 4 pp. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- KaneÕs description of the hardships of the Mormon march. 1846. Draft of article or lecture describing events from Feb., 1846 when first group left Nauvoo, to May, when the second group left. 9 pp. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Difficulties of Mormon emigration after leaving Nauvoo. Draft, perhaps of a letter. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Mormon Journey to Salt Lake. Notes and descriptions, perhaps from a journal. 10 pp. [1847-1849]. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Copies of letters re. right of Mormons to pass through Indian territory. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - a. Mitchell, R. B. to T[homas] H. Harvey. 1 p. arrival of Mormons at Council Bluffs. Jun. 29, [1846].
  - b. Harvey, T[homas] H. to W[illia]m Medill. 1p. Jul. 13, 1846.
  - c. Medill, W[illiam] to Thomas H. Harvey. 3 pp. Sept. 2, 1846.
- Copies of letters re. agreement of Potawatomi Indians to let Mormons winter in their country. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - a. Richards, Willard to [Thomas L.] Kane. 1p. Aug. 19, 1846.
  - b. Young, Brigham to Col. Kearney, Capt. Clary, Major Swords or C-O at Ft. Leavenworth. Description of KaneÕs illness, 2 pp. Aug. 10, 1846.
  - c. Edes, H. G. W. - medical report on Kane. 1 p. Aug. 19, 1846.
  - d. incomplete copies of above. 2 pp.
  - e. Potawatomi Indians. Agreement, 1p. Jul. 2., 1846.
  - f. Allen, J. (Lt. Col. cmdg. Mormon Battalion). Approval, 1 p. Jul. 10, 1846.
- Copies of letters re. wintering of Mormons in Indian territory. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - a. [Medill, William] to J. K. Kane. Conditional permit, 1 p. Sept. 3, 1846.
  - b. Medill, W[illiam] to Thomas H. Harvey. 2 pp. Sept. 2, 1846.
  - c. Allen, J. to J. C. Little. Praising Mormon Battalion. 1 p. Jul. 20, 1846.
- Unknown to [Thomas L.] Kane. Nov. 12, 1846.Draft of unsigned letter from member of Mormon Battalion written from Chihuahua, Mexico. 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Copies of letters re. conditions and movements of Mormons, 1846. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - a. Harvey, Th[omas] H. to W[illia]m Medill. Description of Camp of Israel. 5 pp. Dec. 3, 1846.
  - b. Cutler, Alpheus to [Thomas H. Harvey]. 2 pp. Nov. 3, 1846.
  - c. Harvey, Th[omas] H. to Alpheus Cutler. 1 p. Nov. 5, 1846.
  - d. Cutler, Alpheus to [Thomas H. Harvey] [or Clayton?]. 5 pp. with docket notes. Nov. 6, 1846.
- [Kane, Thomas L.] to [? Sec. of War, Marcy, or President Polk]. n.d. (1847?). Draft, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Trials of the Mormons [1846-47] - draft of letter, n.d., description of deserted Nauvoo. 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- KaneÕs description of his Mormon mission [1847] draft letter of letter, n.d., 7 pp. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Kane, Thomas L. to William Medill, Apr. 2, 1847,3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Kane, Thomas L. to [W. L.] Marcy, Apr. 21, 1847,4 pp. (see also folder #24) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Medill, W[illiam] to W. L. Marcy, Apr. 24, 1847,8 pp. report through Marcy to the President on Mormon migration. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Kane, Thomas L. - Report on Mormons [1847] 8 pp. including 1 p. draft (letter to Medill or other official, docketed ÒPresdts Report No. 2 contg. CensusÓ) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- [Kane, Thomas L.] to [? James K. Polk or W. L. Marcy] [1847], 5 pp. draft with notes (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Copies of letters to Medill from Kane re. Permission for Mormons to winter near Council Bluffs. n.d. (probably 1847 or Ô46), 15 pp. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Draft of letter by Kane to Mormon friend, after KaneÕs return East [1847], 1 p. (ans. to #20 ?) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- [Kane, Thomas L.] to [Horace] Greeley, [Aug., 1847?]Description of Utah shortly after original group of Mormons arrived. 9 pp. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Draft of Kane letter to high official re. Mormons [1848], 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Description of discovery of gold, 1 p. Sidney and Ira Willis and others of [Mormon] Battalion working for Sutter. [1848] (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Letter from Kane re. Utah and Free Soil. (Kane made chairman of Free Soil Central Com. in 1848) n.d., 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Woodruff, Wilford to [Thomas L.] Kane, Dec. 4, 1849,1 p. defending Mormons. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Fragment of prelim. letter by Kane on Free Soil question. [Dec. 4, 1849] 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Kane report on meeting on behalf of Mormons [1850] Draft of speech, 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Richards, F. D. to T[homas] L. Kane, Oct. 30, 1851,Lecture on Mormons, 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- ÒThe Mormon Outrages at Salt LakeÓ - clipping from Philadelphia newspaper, Nov. 1851,including letter of Sept. 20, from Salt Lake. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- [New York Herald, May 27, 1852]- clipping describing Mormon settlement and life. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Bernhisel, John M. to [Thomas L.] Kane, Dec. 9, 1857,2 pp. and cover. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- [OÕBrien, Fitz James] - clipping of poem on death of Elisha Kent Kane, 1857. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- [Kane, Thomas L.] to Gov. Cummings, [1857],1 p. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Kane letter (draft) to high official on DrummondÕs accusation against Mormons [1857], 2 pp. docketed on back as Apr. 27, 1857. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Diary I - Jan. 8, 1858 to Jan. 28, 1858.Sea voyage from New York, across Isthmus of Panama and to San Francisco, pressed leaves, etc. in back. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Diary II - Jan. 29, 1858 to May 10, 1858.San Francisco to San Pedro by ship, Feb. 8 or 9 left San Bernardino for Salt Lake. Includes account of departure from Fern Rock, Jan. 4, partly out of order and illegible, contains letters, notes, maps and diagrams. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- ÒMormon Martyrs" (of San Bernardino) - clipping from San Francisco paper of May 3, 1858,article by Wallach from Los Angeles dated Apr. 22 or 28, 1858. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Kane, Thomas L. to Eli K. Price, Jul. 30,. 1858.severing relations with govÕt. in efforts on behalf of Mormons, 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Kane letter (draft) to official, perhaps Buchanan, on behalf of Mormons. [1850?], 8 pp. (see also folders #35 and #37). (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Young, Brigham to Thomas L. Kane, Jan. 14, 1859,5 pp. and cover. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Forney, John W. to Thomas L. Kane, Jan. 23, 1867,at time of threatened impeachment of Johnson. 3 pp. and cover. (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Deseret News (Salt Lake City), Dec. 26 and 28, 1883.clippings, KaneÕs death. (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Juvenile Instructor, Jan. 15, 1884.clipping, KaneÕs death. (Salt Lake City paper). (Box 1, Folder 54)
- National Tribune (Washington, D. C.), 1886.clipping, ÒBucktail RegimentÓ - KaneÕs Civil War Regiment. (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Quasi-biblical descriptive matter in KaneÕs hand. 5 pp. notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
- ÒPlea of a condemned manÓ. provenance uncertain, not related to western material, 2 pp. draft, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Genealogy of Dennistown family. Mrs. Kane was Elizabeth Dennistoun Wood. 13 pp. and wax seal, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Short dissertation on state sovereignty. 2 pp. notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Democracy and rule of the people. 1 p. draft. (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Part of an account of the ÒMahaw massacreÓ, n.d., 4 pp. (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Notes on Mormons and their history. n.d., 4 pp. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Fragments. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - a. 2 pp. notes - arrival in Omaha territory, poetic.
  - b. part of letter, n.d. - about meeting, 1 p.